准备好了吗  孩子们
Are you ready, kids?
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
我听不见
I can't hear you
好了船长
Aye aye, captain
是谁住在深海的大菠萝里
Who lives in a pineapple under the sea?
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
方方黄黄伸缩自如
Absorbent and yellow and porous is he
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
如果四处探险是你的愿望
If nautical nonsense be something you wish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
那就敲敲甲板让大鱼开路
Then drop on the deck and flop like a fish
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
准备
Ready
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob SquarePants
植树节大乱
编剧
翻译: 1440kHz
分镜总监
指导总监
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
煎饼好好吃  珊迪
These pancakes are delicious, Sandy
不过这个甜甜的东西是什么
But what do you call this sweet stuff?
那是枫糖浆
That's maple syrup
差不多就像是从树上流下来的酱
It's kinda like jelly that comes from trees
树上流的酱
Tree jelly?
恶心
Gross
我宁愿现挤现吃
I prefer mine on tap
欢迎来到裤头村
Welcome to Bikini Bottom's
第一届植树节庆祝活动
very first Arbor Day celebration
理发节
Barber Day?
[ Barber（理发师）与 arbor（树木）谐音 ]
我倒挺需要稍微给头理一下
Well, I could use a trim
她说的应该是海港节
I think she said Harbor Day
[ Harbor（海港）与 arbor（树木）谐音 ]
专门给我这样的老海军庆功
to celebrate old Navy swabs like meself
是植树节
It's Ar-bor Day
专门庆祝植树喜悦的心情
It's a day to celebrate the joy of trees
可是珊迪
But, Sandy
全裤头村就只有你有唯一一棵树
you've got the only tree in town
没错  只有我有树的日子已经到头了
Correction, I used to have the only tree
因为今天大家都可以自己种树了
'cause today you're all gonna grow your own tree
海里长不出树吧
Trees don't grow underwater
这些小家伙长得出来哦
These little fellers will
我利用科学的力量
I've used the power of science
造出了可以长出海水树的特制橡子
to make special acrons
that will grow into saltwater trees
你好啊  小树苗
Hello, little tree
进来吧
There you go
快看啊
Look at that
不能放嘴里嚼  你个榆木脑袋
You don't need to chew it, you whittle stick
要想保持树木健康  你们就只要
To keep your tree healthy, all you need to do
给树木多多施肥
is give it lots of fertilizer
不成问题
Not a problem
还有一件事
One more thing
要想长出全面发展的快乐小树
to grow a happy, well-rounded tree
就得多跟树说说话
You need to talk to 'em
嗨  我是海绵宝宝
Hi, I'm SpongeBob
小家伙
Hey, little feller
测试  测试
Testing, testing
你好
Hello
我就爱向懂得保守秘密的人倾诉
I love talking to someone who knows how to keep a secret
总算可以跟别人说出
I can finally tell someone
滑浪学校
我在贝壳城抢劫那会儿的事实真相了
what really happened
when I pulled that job in Shell City
你放心  小家伙
Don't worry, little fella
等下就有不少人来跟你说话了
You'll have lots of people talking to you
不好意思
Excuse me
我要找这里的老板谈话
I would like to speak to the proprietor
投诉部门在那
The complaint department's over there
跟那棵树说去吧
Talk to the tree
树先生
Mr. Tree
投诉
我蟹黄堡上的调料分配得太烂了
the condiment distribution of my patty is subpar
要是跟树说话能让树长得更好
If talking to a tree is good for it
那么抒情爵士一定会有奇效
I'll bet a little smooth jazz must be amazing
我就用大自然的方式跟你说话好了
I'll talk to you the way nature intended
让电视跟你说
with television
我的藤壶妈妈
现在回到  我的藤壶妈妈
We now return to “My Mother the Barnacle”
我好爱看
I love this one
谁是可爱小树苗
Who's a cutesy wittle tree?
就是你
You are
想不想听睡前故事啊
Would you like to hear a bedtime story?
很久很久一段肥料以前
Once upon a fertilizer
有棵树妈妈
there was a mama tree
有棵树宝宝
a baby tree
还有棵树爸爸去了森林
and a papa tree who went out to the forest
他们突然碰见了伐木工小金
when they suddenly met little Goldy Lumberjack
破故事一个
What a dumb story
就不能给我闭嘴吗
Would you put a sock in it?
我还要睡觉呢
I'm trying to get some shut-eye
你居然会说话
You can talk?
我要叫你小树皮
I'm gonna name you Barky
给我放手
Let go already
都把我叶子给弄皱了  你个滤食怪
You're wrinkling my leaves, you filter feeding freak
[ 海绵进食方式为滤食 ]
过了一会儿
喂  珊迪
Hello, Sandy?
喂  海绵宝宝
Howdy, SpongeBob
你那棵新树现在怎么样了
How's your new tree doing?
有没有跟它说话啊
Are you talking to it?
我尽力了  不过实话实说
I'm trying, but to be honest
我一句话都说不上来
I really haven't been able to get a word in edgewise
话全被我树给抢了
My tree's been doing all the talking
你没事吧  海绵宝宝
Are you feeling okay, SpongeBob?
先等一下
Hang on
小树皮想跟你说话
Barky wants to talk to you
你干嘛要让我
Why did you leave me
跟这个傻笑带洞黄方块混一起
with this giggling hunk o' holes?
他智力
He's dimmer
比停电期间半瓦功率的灯泡亮度还低
than a half-watt bulb in a power outage
可真是个好家伙啊
Well, smack my tail and call me twitchy
我马上就到
I'll be right there
给我带杯水来
Bring me a glass of water
给我把土换掉
Change my soil
小心别伤到根了
Look out for the roots
你口气太臭了
Your breath smells
你怎么只有脸没身体
Why are you all face and no body?
老弟
Doggy
这棵小树苗可真会聊
This little shrub is a real chatterbox
带我从这个垃圾场里出去
Get me out of this dump
我这种敏感的小树苗得晒太阳才能活
A sensitive tree like me needs sun
外面太冷了
It's too cold out here
太阳太亮了
The sun is too bright
快给我拿毛衣过来
Somebody get me a sweater
我要回房里去
I want to go back inside
我要造出来的是海水树
I wanted to make saltwater trees
可这棵树攻击性也太强太嗨了
but this one's a bit too salty
不知道其他人的树怎么样了
I wonder how everyone else's trees are doing
我不该让这树开船的
I shouldn't have let him drive
起码泡芙老师挺高兴的
At least Mrs. Puff is having a good time
不好意思
Excuse me
这个蟹黄堡太难吃了
but this Krabby Patty tastes awful
你太难看了
Well, you look awful
不过我不会向你抗议的
but you don't hear me complaining
冒犯到我了
I am offended
没礼貌
And offensive
恶心  什么味道那么臭
PU, what stinks?
这边到底是来客人了
Is that the customers
还是收垃圾的开始送外卖了
or has the garbage man started making deliveries?
我要走了
I'm outta here
这里本来还好端端的
This used to be a respectable place
大家都在抗议我投诉部门搞抗议
People are complaining about
me complaint department complaining
什么声音这么难听
What is that horrible noise?
你该把那玩意登记成致命武器
You should register that thing as a lethal weapon
什么
What?
没事的  兄弟
It's okay, buddy
天赋不是万能的
Talent isn't everything
你这种情况就是无能
In your case, it's nothing
现在回到  海胆哥与败蜗子秀
And now back to "The Sir Urchin & Snail Fail Show"
海胆哥与败蜗子秀
你可恶
Why you
我哪有
What I do?
我才一天年纪
I'm just one day old
都知道就只有小屁孩才看这节目
and even I can see this show is for babies
你是不是听不懂
You don't get it, do you?
听什么
Get what?
给我滚出去
Out you go
我自由了
I'm free
兜风兜完了
This joyride is over
意思是我没驾照了吗
Does this mean I don't get my license?
喂  警察局吗
Hello, police department?
我有贝壳城抢劫案的线索
I got a lead on that Shell City job
章鱼哥  你理发师打电话过来了
Hey, Squidward, your barber called
他说他对不起你
He said he's sorry
庸俗
Philistine
小的们走吧
Come on, boys
一起开心玩
Let's have some fun
兄弟  等我先洗完
Hey, buddy, wait your turn
放松
Relax
这样可以帮你们长得又大又壮
This will help you grow big and strong
谢谢
Thank you
再见了  白痴
So long, chump
她在那
There she is
植树节大乱都是她害的
This Arbor Day anarchy is all her fault
那群树大肆搞破坏
Those trees are ruining everything
我先走了
I gotta go
那群树浑身是木头
They're made of wood
建议直接烧了
I say we burn them
好
Yeah
好  烧了
Yeah, burn 'em
章鱼哥  这样不是植树节的精神所在
Squidward, that's not the spirit of Arbor Day
大家都别急
Everyone, calm down
我有个计划
I've got a plan
欢迎大家前来观赏树木大聚会
Come one, come all to Log-a-palooza
这是欢庆植树节的盛大表演
It's an Arbor Day extravaganza
还有肥料可以吃
All you can eat fertilizer
树木可以免费到场观看
If you're a tree, you get in free
大家好
Howdy, folks
你们树根是不是发皱了
Are your roots too wrinkly?
你们树叶是不是发蔫了
Are your leaves feeling wilted?
我树皮摸着有点粗糙
My bark is feeling a little rough
那就来试用一下我的神奇美容机器
Then try my wonderful makeover machine
树木复苏机
the Arbor Revitalizer
过植树节也得美美的
Look your best this Arbor Day
有谁要自愿上台来吗
Do I have any volunteers?
好  我这就试用一下你那个破铜烂铁
Yeah, I'll give your dumb machine a try
快逃  保叶要紧
Run for your leaves
大家先别走
Everyone wait
我好爱
I love it
我本来命中注定要烂在林中一角
I was destined to rot in the woods somewhere
但现在看看我
but look at me now
我变椅子了
I'm a chair
身体从来没感觉这么光滑过
I've never felt so smooth
他样子确实挺帅
He does look pretty handsome
我也想变椅子
I want to be a chair, too
我想变柜子
I want to be a credenza
我想变锯木架
I want to be a sawhorse
我想变桌子
I want to be a table
我
Me
我要下一个  我要下一个
Me next, me next
他们椅子真好
These guys are great
你办法想得真好  珊迪
Good thinking, Sandy
把树变家具真的让树不闹腾了
Furniturizing really calmed these trees down
好耶  椅子最强
Yeah, chairs rule
起码大多数还是不闹腾了
Well, most of them anyway
明年还是不过植树节好了
I think I'll skip Arbor Day next year
窃牙记
编剧
分镜总监
翻译: 1440kHz
分镜指导
动画总监
统筹
监制
本字幕仅限学习交流
严禁用于商业用途
客串
嗨  派大星
Hi, Patrick
我又过了美好的一
I just had another great--
等一下
wait a minute
怎么了
What's wrong?
我长鼻子了
I think I'm growing a nose
我不要鼻子
I don't want a nose
派大星  等等
Patrick, wait
派大星你看
Look, Patrick
你掉了一颗牙
You just lost a tooth
晚上把牙齿放枕头底下的话
And if you put that tooth under your pillow tonight
牙仙子就会过来取走牙齿
the Tooth Fairy with come and take the tooth
然后给你留下两毛五
and leave you a quarter
一颗牙值两毛五
A quarter for just one tooth?
中奖了
Jackpot
当晚
晚安  牙牙
Good night, teethies
犯罪生活就是回报多多
Who says a life of crime doesn't pay?
怎么
What the--
睡拳
Sleep punch
多余闪粉
谁往那走了
Who goes there?
是牙仙子
The Tooth Fairy
一定要给海绵宝宝看
I gotta show SpongeBob
搞什么
Come on
海绵宝宝
SpongeBob
你说得对
You were right
牙仙子过来了  我还抓到他了
The Tooth Fairy came, and I got him
我没偷东西
I didn't do it
派大星  你你
Patrick, you-you-
你真的抓到了牙仙子
you really did catch the Tooth Fairy
就跟你说吧
I told ya
他没给我两毛五  不过你看
He didn't give me a quarter, but look
我在他袋子里发现了奇珍异宝
I found these precious jewels in his bag
你们俩白痴在唠叨什么
What are you chowderheads yapping about?
还什么牙仙子
Tooth Fairy?
你放心
Don't worry
没必要对着咱俩装傻
You don't have to play dumb with us
你秘密不会暴露的
Your secret is safe
今晚带我们跟你一起走吧
Please let us ride along with you tonight
让咱当你的牙仙子小助手
And be your Tooth Fairy assistants
没错
Yeah
我就是牙仙子
I'm the Tooth Fairy
我需要有人来帮我趁火打劫
And I could use a little help scoring loot--
我是说  收集牙齿
I mean, collecting teeth
今晚一定很漫长
It's gonna be a long night
这里一定可以找到牙齿
I bet we could find some teeth here
停车
Pull over
这位老是喝汽水
Now, this guy drinks a lot of soda
一定有几颗松动的牙齿可以取走
so I'm sure he's got a few loose teeth for us
一起抓住他
Let's get him
来  戴上特制牙仙子面罩
Here, use these special Tooth Fairy masks
太不专业了
Amateurs
快看  是海霸
Look, it's Bubble--
闭嘴
Can it
不然你们两个笨蛋
Now, why don't you mugs
到这位小个子的身上找牙齿吧
shake down Tiny here for some teeth?
我到那边那堆贵重物品去找牙齿
I'm gonna look for teeth in those valuables over there
只有牙仙子才可以这么笑
Only the Tooth Fairy gets to laugh like that
我没摸到牙齿  派大星
I don't feel any teeth, Patrick
我摸到了不少
Well, I feel a bunch of them
这颗好松
This one's really loose
咱帮忙拔出来  牙仙子一定不会介意
I'm sure the Tooth Fairy won't mind if we help it out
企鹅男孩
Barnacle Boy
放别人枕头底下的钱原来存这里吗
Is this where you keep the pillow money?
牙齿最近还挺值钱
Teeth are sure worth a lot these days
走了  去找更多牙齿了
Come on, let's get more teeth
你的工作最好了
You've got the best job ever
贝臂
对了
Right
你们两个白痴今晚帮了牙仙子不少忙
You stooges really gave the Tooth Fairy
a lot of help tonight
虽然你们害我很头疼
Even if you also gave me a headache
我喜欢帮忙
I like helping
咱还有时间最后再来抢一家
Well, I think we got time for one last job if you're in
蟹老板就住这里
That's where Mr. Krabs lives
他是我白天的老板
He's my daytime boss
你是我晚上的老板
You're my nighttime boss
等等
Wait
小心有陷阱
Watch out for booby traps
我帮蟹老板安装了安保系统
I helped Mr. Krabs install the security system myself
所以
so--
这里就有一个
Here's one
拉我
我来解除警报
I'll disarm it
派大星  不要
Patrick, no
喂
Hello?
谁在楼下
Who's down there?
我要报警了
I'm calling the police
警察吗
Yes, police?
快过来
Come quick
我听到有声音
I heard a noise
不好  吵醒蟹老板了
Oh, no, we woke him up
快逃出去
Let's get out of here
海绵宝宝  派大星
SpongeBob, Patrick
你们到底是在干什么
What in the name of Poseidon's pantaloons are you doing?
你们为什么触发了我的小偷警报
Why have you tripped me burglar alarm?
你们为什么背着小偷袋子
And why do you have those burglar sacks?
你们为什么戴着小偷面罩
And why are you wearing burglar masks?
你们为什么跟着那个小偷
And why are you with that burglar?
等一下
Wait a minute
你们是小偷吗
Are you burglars?
我要来份加了奶酪的小偷
I'll take a burglar with cheese
我们不是小偷
We're not burglars
我们只是在给牙仙子当助手
We were just assisting the Tooth Fairy here
你好
Hello
那不是牙仙子
That ain't no Tooth Fairy
早该知道的
I should know
我几年前就把牙齿全卖给真牙仙子了
I sold all my teeth to the real Tooth Fairy years ago
完了  警察来了
Oh, no, the fuzz
你们快帮我逃跑
You gotta get me out of here
不好吧
I don't know
蟹老板说你不是真牙仙子
Mr. Krabs says you're not the real Tooth Fairy
我当然是真的了
Of course I am
你们一定要相信我
You just gotta believe
就是这样
That's all, yeah
我相信你  牙仙子
I believe in you, Tooth Fairy
再见  蟹老板
Goodbye, Mr. Krabs
他们两个也太好骗了
Those two are so gullible
拉我
快看
Look
绳子上面写  拉我
This rope says "pull me"
不能再往前走了
We can't go any farther
完蛋了
The jig is up
该怎么办才好
What are we gonna do?
你可是牙仙子啊
You're a Tooth Fairy
你会飞
You can fly
飞向安全地带
Fly to safety
什么
What?
飞吧
Fly
别忘了带上牙齿
Don't forget your teeth
还有船
Or your boat
派大星  我好像感觉
You know, Patrick, I get the feeling
那不是真牙仙子
that wasn't the real Tooth Fairy
当然不是了
Of course not
我才是
But I am
真牙仙子
The real Tooth Fairy?
你们整晚都在努力收集牙齿
You two did a wonderful job collecting teeth all night
因此  我要让你们成为
Therefore, I'm going to make you
牙仙子名誉小助手
honorary Tooth Fairy assistants
阿瓦达
Abraca--
索牙
Dental
来吧
Come on
一颗牙
A tooth
还有两毛五
And a quarter
阿瓦达索牙
Abraca-dental